Okay, let's talk about these three
animals. Thank you for practicing and for being
able to do this. I am very
grateful. Maybe tomorrow, for
$, explain these three
animals. You have to show.
Okay, okay, let's talk about this.
Ah, the one below looks like a cow, but it's
really a
pig. It looks like a cow with a
dog's head, but it's a
pig. Let's say someone criticizes you.
How does the pig think? The
pig says, "This person is a bad
person. This person
criticized me." No, the pig says, "No,
first, it doesn't understand that they are its
own
seeds." There's a joke at the
Diamond Mountain retreat center.
We had a very
long teaching that all
stupid people come from
[Music].
Then a lady came to the
program. She was a very
irritating person, and she said, "One day, she stood up and
said, 'This Diamond Mountain is a
horrible place. I am surrounded by people like this.' Just like
the pig doesn't
understand." And because the pig doesn't
understand, the pig gets
angry. And that's the
snake. And then the hen or the
rooster.
And sometimes they paint a
dove. It means
desire. It's not wrong to want
things. It's
okay. In a Buddha's paradise,
everything is
beautiful. It's
always
beautiful. It's not wrong to desire a
Beautiful life. It's not wrong to want a Tesla. A
Tesla car is
fun. What's this about the rooster? Because we're
not supposed to have
wishes. That rooster isn't a
normal wish. That rooster is a
stupid wish. What's the difference between an
intelligent wish and a stupid wish? What he
said is that an
intelligent wish—let's say you want a
Tesla car—an
intelligent wish helps other people
get
Tesla cars. For
example,
last week, those two women from
Ukraine, their house was being
bombed, people around them were
dying. We got them out of there, we took them
to Arizona, which is maybe worse than
Ukraine, I don't
know. [Laughter] But we brought them over, and Rob is going to
buy them a car this
week.
We found
donors, and they're going to buy them a
new car this
week.
Right, people are asking where their
families are, where their husbands and
children are. One has a 12-
year-old son. We can bring him over, I think, in the
next week or two,
and they can't leave the
country. So we're trying to
prepare a place for
them where they can
arrive. So, as it usually happens, the
wife is doing all the
work, and the husbands arrive
later, then the children.  Those who are 30
years old can't come until
the
war is over, and what it says
here... So it's not wrong to want
things, what's wrong is hurting
someone else to
get them.
The stupidest way to get more
land for your country is to try to
take it from another
country. The best way to have more land
for your country is by sharing your land
with another
country. But it's not wrong to want more land, it's
okay.
The way you get it is when you
give it to
someone else. That's the opposite of
war. As long as human beings keep
wanting to take land, when they want
land they
need it, and they need teachers. That's why
the teachers from
Guadalajara are going on tour in
Latin America.
And Grandpa and my friends are going to
find a way to pay for
the
passage. In English they say, "
Stick your finger in the cake, your
finger in the caramel,
give
something to the caramel."
[Music]
Latin America,
these three animals are the cause of
having an unhappy life.
[Laughter]
In the... when you try to take the
problem away from someone
else, part of the practice of...  Taking
someone
else's problems away is very sweet, doing it
anonymously. As Jesus said
in his time, there was a very
good custom of fasting, not eating in the
morning, and he said, "When you are fasting,
keep it a
secret, try not to look hungry."
What happened? You're
fasting, so you're supposed to keep it
a
secret. There's a practice
here: take other people's problems away.
Do it
anonymously and try to feel that you're also
taking their problems away.
Who's bombing
Kev?
Kev's people. They're bombing
K. Other people are just
instruments of
animals. When you meet
someone who makes you angry, they
come from
you. All
annoying people come from
you. Excuse my bad language, don't
tell
Veronica. All idiots come from
another
idiot, and that's you.
All those who bomb the city
come from
you. If the
Latin American tour is successful, people will
start to
understand, and we can stop the
bombing. In the Vietnam War, they put me
in
jail. I did a  I was protesting against
this
war. I was living with some
priests. There were like a couple hundred
people in
jail. After 24 hours, he came and
rescued me. He did
n't do anything. He said something to the people in the
prison, and I got out. I was the only one,
and many of my
friends said, "This is nonsense. They put us
in
jail. We stayed in the lab. It's a
bomb. Stupid. We ca
n't stop the
war." In fact, how do we stop the
war? We have to stop our proposals.
Anger comes from
that. So don't tell me you can't
do anything to stop that war. Yes, you
can. If you turn on the news and see the
news about the
war, that news comes from
you. While you're watching the news,
there's something wrong with you.
Everyone has a chance to stop
the
war. We can all stop the
war because we create the
war. So stop being angry at your
relatives. Control your
mind, and then the war will
stop. You do
n't have to do
this. Just stop sowing the
seeds. We all have the power to
stop a war that's
10 miles
away, and it's
incredible. So what it says
here is, if you are a very
strong person, when you take away the pain from...
Imagine the others are also
taking away their three
animals. I'm going to invite you to the
United States and get you a
visa. I commit to paying for your
expenses.
We committed for
two years. Rob, that's all.
After that, you have to go to
work. By the way, you're going to work in the cafe.
As long as you decide, you're going to
work in the cafe.
Anyay Expes, I'm going to pay your
expenses for two
years.
But while I
pay your expenses, I'm taking away
your... and I'm also going to take away your
pig. You don't understand the
pig, and I'm going to take it
away, and I'm also going to eat your
incorrect understanding. First level of practice: I'm
going to take away your
pain. I'm going to take you out of K and
bring you to my house, and I'm going to pay your
expenses. But on a
deeper level, I'm going to take away your
incorrect understanding and destroy it. In the...
Dey, to remove the...
If you are a person, a true practitioner of
Loong, it
's not enough to take away their
pain. You have to eat their pig,
also take away their incorrect understanding.
[Music] I did
n't try to find something like Walt
Disney in the book...  It's called the city of
happiness, and the next theme is the
city of
happiness.
What causes conflict in the
world? If you look for the tsag taga, it means
the root. If you look for the
root, it's my habit of taking care of myself
first. Who caused the war in
Europe? We did, each one of us.
How did we cause it?
I took care of myself
first, and that created the war. It's
very
deep. Everyone has the power to
stop the
war. Even if you're sitting in
Guadalajara, you have the power to stop the
war. Stop taking care of yourself first.
Take care of others
first. The war will
stop. The war comes from
[Music]
us. If you know that the war is
happening, why are you taking care of yourself
first?
Bad suede.
Personally, you should feel more
and more
[Music]
much more
relaxed. You had a bad
day. That's
incredible. I'm very happy that you had a
bad day.
I thought you were a Buddhist because you're
happy, and you had a bad
day. Think about how many bad seeds
you burned. We should have a
celebration whenever something terrible
happens to a practitioner.
Like, I'm so happy that that
seed... if I had waited until
tomorrow, I would already be that seed.  That
negative seed would be the
[Applause]
double says Problems are your
[Music]
friend and don't think they're a problem
I want to say a bad word but I know
my wife doesn't always
try it whenever
something
ruins being
happy so many bad seeds open
today
today I'm so
happy that's a true
practitioner
when you can think So you've traveled
to the city of
happiness and that's the picture that was
there how you get to the city of
happiness
rejoice when you have
problems all
idiots all idiots can be
happy all idiots can be
happy when things are going
well Any fool can be
happy
the sign of a true
practitioner is that you're also happy
when things are going
badly if you're happy when things are going
badly and if you're happy when things are
going well How often are you
happy
always that's a true practitioner [
Music]
those people you know who are always
happy It's not that they don't have
problems it's that they
know how to change the problem
into
happiness when you
find they're going through terrible things
in their
personal life But they know how to transform it
into
happiness they're happy that they're
burning their bad
seeds there's another
Technique
means that normally if you,
you all, or we have a problem,
we feel overwhelmed by it.
I was going to
sing a song in Guadalajara, and the
microphone stopped working. At that
moment, it was
terrible. And then he says, if you are a
true Buddhist,
you learn to use problems to
help you. And he gives an
example: In Tibet, there were no
cars. My teacher asked me to
teach him to
drive. He had never even seen
a bicycle
in his entire life. In Tibet, there wasn't a
single
car, and he said, "Can you teach me to
drive a
car?" And I was very foolish because I
said yes. It took me
like
years. I almost died many
times. I remember one day
[Music]
we were driving through a very
small neighborhood, and someone was with their
lawnmower and had like three trash cans
waiting for the garbage truck to come
in front of the
house. The teacher had a problem when he was
driving; his eyes were connected.
So he was
driving, and then I told him to be
careful, and
[Laughter] he
said, and he hit all the trash cans,
boom, and he crushed all the
trash cans. Then the one with the lawnmower,
and we  Excuse me, excuse me,
and I said no. Let's go to the
freeway, and he was going 20 miles per hour
on a 75-mile-per-
hour freeway, and then someone passed by and he gave him the
special signal and said, "And what does that
mean?" It's just a
welcome sign.
In the city, there are
no
cars, and when they go to another
city to sell
things, they have to walk, and they take a
horse, and it starts to
rain. If you're the kind of person who
says, "I'm so happy it's
raining," because thieves don't
like to go out when the
weather is bad, by the way. If you don't want to get mugged
in New York City, just
walk around at 5 in the
morning.
All the thieves are asleep; they don't
like to get up
early, or maybe they're watching
shows. It means you can find something
good in any
problem. You can say, "I'm so happy it's
raining."
We understand the problem of the
[Laughter]
rain. It's very
heavy. It means that I always find something good in any problem.
PR,
this is about how to use the problem for
something
good. You can use any problem
for something
good, like I had a problem with my
coffee, the black coffee.
[Laughter]
When money gets close to the cafe, it
disappears. Sometimes I call it the
black hole cafe. We couldn't get all the
permits to
open. So many permits and
licenses. The local government people
are either very lazy or they're waiting for
something. And I had a
personal policy: I don't bribe them.
So the opening kept getting
delayed. It's
a
problem, but it's a skill in
life. When you have a problem,
use it and get something good out of it.
So I made a recording studio in
the cafe and we created Peach
World because you don't need a license
to sell
food. We opened the cafe and made Peach
World
News. So the problem became
a great
benefit. All problems can be
used.
So open your
mind. Don't be like, "I have a
problem, the government isn't going to give me the
permit. Shut up." It's something
amazing. That's a new
[Music]
mantra.
[Laughter]
Shut up and something good. Shut up and the
good old
Tusas show is much more important than
the
cafe. It helps a lot.
Everyone
loses,
and it's
actually... If you  You're really good at
turning problems into
opportunities. You're going to start praying, "I hope I
have a
problem today. God, please send me an
extra problem, one more problem.
I need more opportunities." That's why you're
here. Don't complain for the next six
months. Only happy faces.
Go, Daniel, why do you look so
happy?
Give another
example: when you're walking in the
rain in Tibet, another city, selling
things, and the thieves don't
bother you.
When the rain stops and it starts
to
snow
in Tibet, they don't have good locks
for the
horses, so the horses break
their hooves on the
rocks. But when it snows, it's like an
automatic cushion; the horses' hooves
never break during the snow. I never
know.
[Music]
Walking from
Guadalajara, traveling from Guadalajara,
Chalapa, and don't tell me that's wrong.
[Laughter] I've
said it a
lot. You
can always find something
positive in your
problems, and I say you can always
profit from your
problems. After we opened the Peach show, before
the
cafe, we had already made a
profit, like what the cafe earns
in six
months. So just be happy
with the
problems and learn to
Use them, we have 12 minutes left,
right? It
was a great
[Music]
video. I'm going to transform this problem into
an
opportunity. A very famous verse said, "
I use this quote every
day. When you have a
problem, if there is something you can do about it,
then please
do it. If you have a problem
and there is nothing you can do about it,
then please
relax. End of
story." That's Shantideva. I'm going to
say it again: If you have a
problem, if there is something you can do about it,
then please be quiet and
do it. Don't tell me about your
problems. If you have a
problem and there is nothing you can do about it
today, you can also be
quiet because there is nothing you can
do and just
relax. And it's very
beautiful advice, and you can probably have an
opportunity today to
[Music]
use
mine. And don't think that problems are
something
negative. Problems are empty.
All things are
empty. It is emptiness.
It means that no problem is a
real
problem.
[Music]
If a problem is a problem for you, it's
your
fault. If you can be a super
creative person, all problems
become a great
opportunity, and simply
Decide,
just learn to tell yourself
[Music]
Shut up, people say I want to study
the
diamond path, I want to study
tantra, I want to study the
secret path. I'm going to tell you the
secret path. There's an opportunity in every problem. You just
have to have the
attitude. When a
problem comes your way, it's like a math equation.
In third grade,
my
hope
is like the teacher told you to throw it away. Just like there's
a
problem, there's supposed to be an
opportunity
inside. Just pretend that life
is giving you a
test. It's like a
game. It's
like those TV shows where
you have to guess the
answer. Life is going to give you a
problem. Can you guess the
[Laughter]
opportunity? Try
harder. Life is going to give you
problems. There's an opportunity inside
every
problem. Life wants you to
figure it out. Use it like a
game. Have fun
when you have a problem. Have
fun with it.
There's an opportunity in here.
And everything that happens to you can
become an
opportunity. Use this. I use
this. We started a business with a
loan of $
0.00. It became the largest
jewelry company in the
world, a quarter of a billion.  dollars
every
year. How do you do
that?
Take the problem and find the
opportunity hidden
within. Every problem is an
opportunity to make more money. You just
have to
figure it out. Do that 10 times a day, and
then Warren Buffett will buy your
company. Stop complaining. The time you
spend complaining about problems is a
waste of
time. Just take it as a
riddle, like a
puzzle. Somewhere in this
problem there is an
opportunity. I'm supposed to
figure it out. That's what
meditation is for.
My teacher had a
car accident. Before I
met him, he had a blow to
his
throat, and he spoke just like Star Wars
Darth
Vader. Every problem is an
opportunity. Whenever a
problem comes your way, it's an opportunity to find an
opportunity.
[Music]
If you don't take the problem as an
opportunity, you are the problem.
[Applause]
You're
next. I
hope you learn the
IDs, and then you don't have to memorize
the whole
book. There's a meditation you can
do. You just bring up the images one by
one, and then you can remember
the whole
program. Memorize the
images.
Tomorrow I'm going to
give  For each image we've
had, we've already had 17
images
back, and they don't have the
images. Tomorrow we're going to review the 17
images
we have, and I'm going to give for each
image s
different people, 1
different person who says about this
image. Even people who never
went to the
[Music]
Spring Village are going to have realizations of
lyong if a
disaster happens to them. One of the purposes
of recognizing the suffering of
life. By the way, it's not
depressing. A true
Buddhist master is supposed to tell you that you're going to get old, you're going to get
sick, your face is going to be full of
wrinkles, you're going to forget all the
teachings you've
received, you're going
to die in a
hospital bed, you're going to be a
[Music]
permanent. That's my
job. My job is to tell you all
these
things, but for a person of
that kind of life, it's
perfect. It's full of
opportunities.
Always, whenever something bad happens to you,
you can get something
good out of it. And the lama in this
section says, even
ordinary people understand
this. Some people go to the
Ram Rim retreat in Guadalajara and learn renunciation.
This life is very short and very
painful, so I have to do something about it.
to help
others, and he says it's human nature to
understand
that. A
normal person who has never
heard of
cancer goes to the
hospital and lies there all
day. Those people automatically develop Buddhist attitudes.
Suffering has
this good
quality: they start asking what
will happen
next. The cancer becomes
their
Buddhist Lama, and they start having all these
Buddhist questions. And he says even people
who have never heard of it,
the normal pain they
have, it teaches them to be gentle and
kind to others.
So if you're sitting in this
class, you should be happy when
those things
happen to you. You're going to become a
more
sensitive person, and you're going to understand other people's problems.
When they put me in a
wheelchair at the airport, I felt
compassion for other people in
wheelchairs, and it was the first time
I felt compassion for people in
wheelchairs at the airport.
Then a
real person has to... He's
always saying that
a real person from Lojong
has to go even
deeper. I'm so glad I got
cancer;
now I can do...  All those
meditations he taught me for so many
years. Now I can make
real [Music] and want to go to the
advanced version. A couple of years ago,
my teacher came to Diamond
M. He was the debate teacher
and helped me a lot in my
life. He helped me finish my studies
and came to
visit. On
that day, my
gallbladder got infected. It was extremely
painful, and Venerable Jigme was going to take me
to the hospital. It took two
hours. I actually had to lie on the
floor, and he went for the
car, and everyone was
there. People said, "Michael, I wrote a
prayer for
you. I wrote a long-life prayer
for
you." It took me about six
weeks. "Can you stay for a few
minutes, and I'll
read it to you?" And
I said, "I have to
go," and he said, "No, I'm not going to
read it to you. I'm going to be the first person to
die during your long-
life prayer." So it was a very long prayer.
And then Jigme took me to the
hospital. I was screaming all the way there. It hurts so much, so
painful. And I got there. They put me on [a slingshot/tablet/etc.]. They took me to the hospital. They
did the
surgery. This is a true story.
When I
woke up, there was
a lady who  She was looking at me like,
over
me, and she's
Tibetan. I woke up from the
anesthesia and said, "Who are you?"
[Laughs]
My
name is which means long
life. And I said, "Of
course, that's your
name." And I said, "What are you doing
here?" And she said, "I'm your
doctor." And I said, "
Why?" And I said, "I didn't know there were
Tibetans in
Arizona." And she said, "
Oh, and I'm your
doctor." I was like, "That's
incredible." And the guy next to me had
a
very
dangerous heart transplant, and we became good
friends.
[Music]
Tea the
second. I feel like I'm swimming in
an ocean that's with
warm water. We're going to give it to you. He was next to me. He
was very nervous
because they were going to open his
heart, and we were chatting a
lot, and I was thinking that I already had
a
serious problem, but Loong says that I'm supposed to
take on his problem
too, and it was very
difficult. I
just wanted to say, you know, that curtain. I mean, I
have enough problems. I don't want to.
But if you're a person who,
even when you're having a big
problem, you have to embrace
other people's problems, and in the end, there are more
opportunities. There are more
opportunities when you have a
problem. No.  Try to avoid the
problem. Look for more
problems and take on more
problems. A question from the old books:
If suddenly my mind breaks and they
take me to the asylum, can I stop
having
problems? But one answer is: the
more problems you can take on, the more
capacity
you have,
and the human capacity for problems is
limitless. Every time you think you're
too
tired, every time you think you've taken on
too many problems from
others, you can take on
more. There's
no limit to the number of problems
you can
take on. If the Lama thinks you're not a
good
student, they'll tell you, "Oh, it gets
really hard. Don't worry and watch Netflix
for a
while."
But if the Lama has faith in you and believes in
you, they'll tell you, "Go and look for more
problems." What do you have to do when you're going to be
completely overwhelmed
by so many
problems? The best way to fix the
syndrome of being completely overwhelmed
by too many problems
is to take on more
problems, and you'll feel
better. Do you have that
capacity? Your capacity is
infinite. Don't think you're less than
that. You can take on countless
problems. I'm going to give you 000 for
the
famous phrase, 5 cu
3 cancel.
[Laughter]
[Applause]
Cancelled.
Try here. Here goes the
answer.
You can sleep on the
plane. That's what they say in my
office. You can stay 12 hours of
overtime. You can sleep on the
plane when you fly to Thailand to
buy some diamonds. You can always sleep on
the
plane. You can take
more.
Your capacity is
infinite. Don't believe it when someone
tells you
something
different. [Music] If you're going to break down and
call me, please
rest. Your capacity is
infinite. We finished the introduction to
day 19. We haven't gotten into the
teaching yet. It's like two or three
hours. That was the introduction. The
next
day, and now we're ready to start.
The real
class
means
transforming, and there are different ways to
transform
problems. You can take an action that
transforms
problems, or you can look at the problem in
different ways. And now a new part has arrived. It's
called actions you can take
to transform
problems, and there are four actions he
mentions. I'm going to give you the four
names, and then we're going to take a
break, and when we come back, we're going to
explain them. Number
[Music]
one:
Level up your
karmic bank account.
Just before you do something
important, there's a
[Music]
tradition. Do very  Good karma
quickly, like if you're going to have a very
important business meeting
or you're going to talk to the girl you
met at the
club, do a one-minute
Super Karma accumulation and then
talk to her. There's a
special method right before you do something
important: do a one-minute meditation
to plant very good
seeds. I don't know, I have a friend who's
buying a new
house and someone calls you saying they want to
buy it. Don't call them
back. Do a one-minute
Super Karma accumulation and then talk to them.
What's the other half of
that? Do a
purification. Now, it's two minutes you
have to wait to make the
call before you talk to the
cute guy you met at the
club. One minute Super Karma accumulation,
like what was the worst thing you did in the
last three
days? Just say it. I
watched TV for four or five
hours. Then
you talk to her. It's like an
instant purification and it's very effective. It works
every
time. That's why it became the
biggest company in the
world. It's the fastest-growing company
in the history of
New York City. What's the
secret? Keep
doing it. By the way, I didn't tell anyone, just keep doing it.
Third, first, good karma.
Instant second instant purification
[Music]
Third we call it
torma means you make a small
offering. Churros are very
good, something like that.
We'll talk more about it.
Number
four, ask the dharma protectors for help.
Ask the good spirits to
help you. There's a big discussion among
Buddhist people in
Tibet about a specific dharma protector.
I think it's all
nonsense and I don't get involved at
all and I'm not going to talk about that
protector. But there are thousands of
dharma protectors, 999. They are very sweet and there is no
controversy.
So I'm going to teach you how you ask them for
help. And those are the four
practices. After the
[Music]
break